<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMed 2.0//EN" "http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov:80/entrez/query/static/PubMed.dtd">
<ArticleSet><Article><Journal><PublisherName>Librello</PublisherName><JournalTitle>Challenges in Sustainability</JournalTitle><Issn>2297-6477</Issn><Volume>5</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate PubStatus="epublish"><Year>2017</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>25</Day></PubDate></Journal><ArticleTitle>Identifying Misalignments between Public Participation Process and Context in Urban Development</ArticleTitle><FirstPage>11</FirstPage><LastPage>22</LastPage><ELocationID EIdType="doi">10.12924/cis2017.05020011</ELocationID><Language>EN</Language><AuthorList><Author><FirstName>Matthew</FirstName><LastName>Cohen</LastName><Affiliation>Department of Earth and Environmental Sciences, Furman University, Greenville, SC, USA. matthew.cohen@furman.edu</Affiliation></Author><Author><FirstName>Arnim</FirstName><LastName>Wiek</LastName><Affiliation>School of Sustainability, Arizona State University, Tempe, AZ, USA. arnim.wiek@asu.edu</Affiliation></Author></AuthorList><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pii">cis-5.2.11</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><History><PubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2017</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>12</Day></PubDate><PubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2017</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>12</Day></PubDate><PubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2017</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>03</Day></PubDate></History><Abstract>Public participation is a common element in state-of-the-art urban development projects. Tailoring the public participation process to the local context is a popular strategy for ensuring sufficient turnout and meaningful engagement, but this strategy faces several challenges. Through a review of case studies of public participation in urban development projects, we identify ten typical misalignments between the public participation process and the local context, including the lack of policy maker support, adverse personal circumstances of participants, low collaborative capacity, and mistrust, among others. When a public participation process is not aligned to the local context, the process may generate outcomes that compromise public interests, inequitably distribute benefits among stakeholders, or favor powerful private interests. This study offers caution and guidance to planning practitioners and researchers on how to contextualize public participation in urban development projects through the categorization of common misalignments that ought to be avoided.</Abstract></Article></ArticleSet>
