<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
   xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="research-article"
   dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">cis</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title xml:lang="en">Challenges in Sustainability</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">2297-6477</issn>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Librello</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12924/cis2022.10010001</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Editorial</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Sustainability Transformations: Emerging Pathways Toward Safe and Just
               Futures for People and the Planet</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <name>
                  <surname>Orr</surname>
                  <given-names>Christopher</given-names>
               </name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">*</xref>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">1</xref>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <name>
                  <surname>Kish</surname>
                  <given-names>Katie</given-names>
               </name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">2</xref>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">3</xref>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <aff id="A1">
            <label>*</label>Corresponding author</aff>
         <aff id="A2">
            <label>1</label>Department of Geography and Environmental Management, University of
            Waterloo, Waterloo, Canada</aff>
         <aff id="A3">
            <label>2</label>Ecological Footprint Initiative, York University, Toronto, Canada</aff>
         <aff id="A4">
            <label>3</label>Editor-in-Chief of Challenges in Sustainability, Librello, Basel,
            Switzerland</aff>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <day>05</day>
            <month>04</month>
            <year>2022</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>10</volume>
         <issue>1</issue>
         <fpage>1</fpage>
         <lpage>2</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-year>2005</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <abstract>
            <p>We are pleased to introduce the third special issue in Challenges in Sustainability
               entitled Sustainability transformations: Emerging pathways toward safe and just
               futures for people and the planet.</p>
         </abstract>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd>climate change</kwd>
            <kwd>COVID-19</kwd>
            <kwd>ecological economics</kwd>
            <kwd>policy</kwd>
            <kwd>sustainability transformation</kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p> We are pleased to introduce the third special issue in Challenges in Sustainability
         entitled Sustainability transformations: Emerging pathways toward safe and just futures for
         people and the planet.</p>

      <p> This special issue emerged in partnership with the Canadian Society for Ecological
         Economics (CANSEE) in the context of the global COVID-19 pandemic. The COVID-19 crisis has
         led to many calls for recovery, to rebuild, and to build back better to address the climate
         crisis. But the pandemic has exposed vulnerabilities and tensions inherent in established
         political and economic systems. Existing vulnerabilities and inequalities have exacerbated
         challenges for health and wellbeing, threatened community livelihoods, and empeded efforts
         to achieve ecological stability and integrity. Moreover, tensions have revealed how deeply
         interconnected social, economic, and environmental dimensions of wellbeing are. Simply
         rebuilding to pursue the previous path is neither tenable nor desirable. Instead, the
         current context provides an opportunity to pivot towards safe and just futures for people
         and the planet. This urgent task demands courage, creativity, and experimentation. What
         groups, initiatives, and visions have been seeded or are emerging from the cracks created
         by the pandemic? What features of our systems must be reimagined and what relationships
         must be renegotiated? And what solutions are capable of catalyzing action that supports
         this reorientation?</p>


      <p> CANSEE supports emerging and established sustainability scholars and ecological economists
         in understanding and analyzing sustainability challenges from a perspective that is deeply
         critical of the status quo. Ecological economists have long emphasized the limits of
         attempting to address the climate crisis within an outdated growth-oriented economic
         framework that prioritizes increasing economic activity at the expense of attending to
         quality and ecological integrity. Thus, ecological economists have important contributions
         to make in understanding and supporting sustainability transformations towards just,
         regenerative, and ecological economies.</p>


      <p> This special issue engages with sustainability challenges from an ecological economics
         perspective in the context of recent vulnerabilities, inequalities, injustices, and
         systemic tensions. Papers in this special issue use the lens, critiques, and tools of
         ecological economics to engage with problems at the intersection of ecological and social
         challenges. These contributions focus on multiple levels from the community to
         international scales to inform effective, inclusive, and transformative solutions. They are
         solution-oriented in that they apply ecological economics thinking to explore concrete
         problems that impact human and ecological wellbeing.</p>


      <p> An important contribution of this special issue is real-world application through
         knowledge transfer. Recognizing that solutions are inherently complex and systemic, they
         implicate diverse actors from governments, NGOs, Indigenous groups, activists, businesses
         and civil society. Thus, we encouraged submissions that considered transformative solutions
         to address relationships between different groups, societies, and species in different
         regions and on different timescales. To increase the impact of their research, contributors
         developed publically accessible knowledge transfer pieces such as a policy brief, op-ed or
         related output where appropriate. In addition to knowledge dissemination, authors of these
         pieces often proposed recommendations for concrete steps needed to realize the solutions
         identified. Alongside individual papers, links to and PDFs of these accompanying knowledge
         transfer pieces are also provided.</p>


      <p> We would like to thank CANSEE for their generous support in encouraging scholarship and
         publishing this special issue.</p>

   </body>
   
</article>
