<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMed 2.0//EN" "http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov:80/entrez/query/static/PubMed.dtd">
<ArticleSet><Article><Journal><PublisherName>Librello</PublisherName><JournalTitle>Challenges in Sustainability</JournalTitle><Issn>2297-6477</Issn><Volume>1</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate PubStatus="epublish"><Year>2014</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>27</Day></PubDate></Journal><ArticleTitle>Publishing Sustainability Research Visually: A Film about the Opportunities and Challenges of a Rural Entrepreneurship Initiative in Kenya</ArticleTitle><FirstPage>80</FirstPage><LastPage>81</LastPage><ELocationID EIdType="doi">10.12924/cis2014.01020080</ELocationID><Language>EN</Language><AuthorList><Author><FirstName>Barry</FirstName><LastName>Ness</LastName><Affiliation>Lund University Centre for Sustainability Studies (LUCSUS), P.O. Box 170, SE–221 00, Lund, Sweden. barry.ness@lucsus.lu.se</Affiliation></Author><Author><FirstName>Ann</FirstName><LastName>Akerman</LastName><Affiliation>Lund University Centre for Sustainability Studies (LUCSUS), P.O. Box 170, SE–221 00, Lund, Sweden. ann.akerman@lucsus.lu.se</Affiliation></Author></AuthorList><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pii">cis-1-2-80</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><History><PubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2014</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>17</Day></PubDate><PubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2014</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>18</Day></PubDate></History><Abstract>We have witnessed a large increase in the number of publications on sustainability challenges over the past decade. One important characteristic of the research is with the wide variety of actors that can make use of the results. Sustainability knowledge is often not only relevant for those in academia or policy-making circles, but it can also be useful for decision-makers in a diversity of societal facets and sectors. It is therefore essential that the sustainability research community have access to a diversity of knowledge dissemination outlets, including those that extend beyond the traditional, and often inaccessible, academic publishing realms. One positive development over the past decade in sustainability research reaching broader audiences has been the proliferation of open access publication outlets. The alternative has provided greater access to scientific articles to almost anyone with an Internet connection. But, is this medium of knowledge dissemination sufficient? Are there additional channels that sustainability researchers can use to broadcast knowledge to even broader user groups?</Abstract></Article></ArticleSet>
