<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="research-article"
         dtd-version="3.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">cis</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title xml:lang="en">Challenges in Sustainability</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">2297-6477</issn>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Librello</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12924/cis2015.03010018</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Book Review</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>A Review of "The Politics of Sustainability: Philosophical Perspectives"</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <name>
                  <surname>Goldemberg</surname>
                  <given-names>José</given-names>
               </name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">1</xref>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <aff id="A2">
            <label>1</label>Electrotechnical and Energy Institute (IEE), University of São Paulo (USP), Brazil</aff>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <day>04</day>
            <month>12</month>
            <year>2015</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>3</volume>
         <issue>1</issue>
         <fpage>18</fpage>
         <lpage>19</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-year>2005</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd>ethics</kwd>
            <kwd>intergenerational responsibility</kwd>
            <kwd>philosophical perspectives</kwd>
            <kwd>sustainability</kwd>
            <kwd>technological leapfrogging</kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <related-object id="book1" source-id="isbn:978-1138854291" source-id-type="book">
         <article-title>The Politics of Sustainability: Philosophical Perspectives</article-title>
         <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
               <surname>Birnbacher</surname>
               <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
               <surname>Thorseth</surname>
               <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
         </person-group>
         <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>
         <year>2015</year>
         <fpage>234</fpage>
         <isbn>978-1138854291</isbn>
      </related-object>
      <sec id="s1">
         <label></label>
         <p>
            Concerns about sustainable development are not a recent
            phenomenon. Societal problem-solving efforts within this
            realm have focused on concrete problems such as the
            preservation of fisheries, forests and national reserves.
            ‘The Politics of Sustainability’ has been discussed extensively in literature, particularly after the publication of
            the Brundtland Commission’s ‘Our Common Future’ 
            report in 1987 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R01">1</xref>] emphasizing inter-generational 
            responsibilities involving economic, environmental and social 
            aspects. Among other areas, the authors of the report highlighted the challenge of global climate change resulting
            from, amongst other things, unsustainable patterns of 
            consumption. ‘The Politics of Sustainability: Philosophical Perspectives’, edited by Dieter Birnhacher and May Thorseth,
            brings a new angle into the discussion of the politics of
            sustainable development: ethical considerations.
         </p>
         <p>
            In Part 1, contributors to the book discuss—in a
            somewhat pessimistic tone—the determinants of 
            nonsustainable behavior, which are lack of motivation; 
            institutions stressing and the difficulties the democratic 
            governments face when implementing the actions needed to protect future generations. The authors also underscore the
            challenges in pressuring politicians to make real progress
            through sustainable policies. This is particularly difficult
            given the existence of more immediate short-range 
            challenges such as economic crises, high unemployment, and
            maintaining an upstanding national position in the international political rat-race.
         </p>
         <p>
            In Part 2 of the book, the contributors present and
            discuss the strong moral and philosophical dimensions of
            policy implementation, setting them up, in Part 3, for the
            proposition of establishing a new fourth institution of government beyond the legislative, executive and judicial. This
            branch would be responsible to ensure “that the interest
            of future generations be taken into account within today’s
            decision-making-process”. The proposal is indeed original. Its adoption in democratic countries will face the same
            difficulties as pointed out in Part 1: to implement practical
            actions to reduce greenhouse gas emissions and to protect
            future generations.
         </p>
         <p>
            It is my view, that, governance is more complicated than
            is portrayes in the book and is not completely compatible
            with different democratic systems around the globe. To
            state that “the incentives for politicians in a democratic system are in maintaining power and securing re-election” (p.
            55) is an over simplification. History has demonstrated that
            there have been many occasions in which even problematic politicians or legislative bodies of governments have
            risen to the task of confronting great societal challenges.
            An example is the decision in the United States Congress
            to support President Roosevelt in joining World War II, despite strong societal sentiments for isolationism at the time.
            The existence of great leaders is essential for 
            democracies to move and history has demonstrated that they frequently appear at critical junctions. This is why there is
            optimism with societies in making continuous strides in
            sustainable development, including the more difficult 
            questions such as the elimination of poverty and averting catastrophic changes in the climate.
         </p>
         <p>
            Technology is one powerful instrument. As technical
            solutions improve, they become less expensive. This 
            creates opportunities for developing countries and means they
            do not have to retrace the steps followed by industrialized
            countries; they can “leapfrog” over many of the developmental steps and avoid many of the problems caused by
            industrialization. An example is that of Brazil’s response to
            the problem of greenhouse gas emissions (GHG) from the
            use of gasoline in automobiles. As an alternative, ethanol
            produced from sugarcane (a renewable crop) was used to
            replace a large fraction of the gasoline, thus reducing the
            GHG emissions in the country by approximately 10% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R02">2</xref>].
         </p>
         <p>
            Ethical considerations, of course, are of great 
            importance when democracies move in more sustainable directions. We must not forget, however, that the existence of
            technical solutions can also help governments to implement sustainable solutions at an expeditious pace. This
            book will, undoubtedly, be of great interest to people less
            interested in economics and environment, and/but 
            fundamental to the philosophical perspectives of sustainable development.
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
         <title></title>
         <p>
            José Goldemberg
         </p>
         <p>
            Electrotechnical and Energy Institute (IEE), University of São Paulo (USP), Brasil; E-Mail:
            goldemb@iee.usp.br
         </p>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back>
      <ref-list>
         <ref id="R01">
            <element-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <year>1987</year>
               <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
               <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name>
                     <surname>Brundtland</surname>
                     <given-names>D</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                     <surname>Khalid</surname>
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                     <surname>Agnelli</surname>
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                     <surname>Al-Athel</surname>
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                     <surname>Chidzero</surname>
                     <given-names>S</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                     <surname>Fadika</surname>
                     <given-names>L</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <source>Our Common Future—The World Commission on Environment and Development.</source>               
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="R02">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <year>2007</year>
               <volume>315</volume>
               <issue>5813</issue>
               <fpage>808</fpage>
               <lpage>810</lpage>
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name>
                     <surname>Goldemberg</surname>
                     <given-names>J</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <article-title>Ethanol for a sustainable energy future</article-title>
               <source>science</source>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
