<?xml version="1.0" ?><root><ref>[1] The current article is based on the findings of the research project entitled “Zarz ˛ adzanie bezpieczeństwem w prawie i polityce azylowej i powrotowej Unii Europejskiej w obliczu kryzysu migracyjnego” (Se- curity Management in European Asylum and Return Law and Policy with Regard to the Migration Crisis) registered at no. 2016/23/D/ HS5/00404 and funded by the National Science Centre, Poland.</ref><ref>[2] Kosińska AM. The Creative Role of the European Council in the Area of Managing Asylum Migration and Return of Third-Country Nationals to Their Country of Origin in the Times of the Migration Cri- sis. Research on the Content of the EC’s Conclusions 2011–2017. In: Yearbook of Polish European Studies. vol. 20. Centre for Europe, University of Warsaw; 2017. pp. 101–127.</ref><ref>[3] Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union. European Union; 2016. C202. Available from: https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal- content/EN/TXT/PDF/?uri=OJ:C:2016:202:FULL&amp;from=EN.</ref><ref>[4] Hartley T. The Foundations of European Union Law. Oxford Univer- sity Press; 2010. doi:10.1093/he/9780199566754.001.0001.</ref><ref>[5] Lelieveldt H, Princen S. Analysing the EU. In: The Politics of the European Union. Cambridge University Press;. pp. 31–50. doi:10.1017/cbo9780511984693.003.</ref><ref>[6] Dawson M. The Governance of EU Fundamental Rights. Cam- bridge University Press; 2017. doi:10.1017/9781107707436. The author also emphasizes that the Fundamental Rights Governance in the EU is based on the principle of exercising the above rights in certain specific political communities. Hence, the key role in the re- alization of those guarantees is played by the constitutional systems of the Member States.</ref><ref>[7] Annual Report on the Situation of Asylum in the European Union 2015. European Asylum Support Office; 2016. doi:10.2847/704455.</ref><ref>[8] Communication from the Commission to the European Par- liament, the Council, the European Economic and So- cial Committee and the Committee of the Regions. A European Agenda on Migration. Brussels, BE: Euro- pean Comission; 2015. COM(2015) 240 final. Available from: https://ec.europa.eu/anti-trafficking/sites/antitrafficking/files/ communication_on_the_european_agenda_on_migration_en.pdf.</ref><ref>[9] Council Decision (EU) 2015/1601 of 22 September 2015 establish- ing provisional measures in the area of international protection for the benefit of Italy and Greece. European Union;. L 248/80. Avail- able from: https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/PDF/ ?uri=CELEX:32015D1601&amp;from=EN.</ref><ref>[10] Policy Department C: Citizen’s Rights and Constitutional Affairs. Internal Border Controls in the Schengen Area: Is Schengen Crisis- Proof, Study for the LIBE Committee. European Parliament; 2016. Available from: https://www.europarl.europa.eu/RegData/etudes/ STUD/2016/571356/IPOL_STU%282016%29571356_EN.pdf.</ref><ref>[11] Kosińska AM, Barbara M. Does the Right to Migration Security Al- ready Exist? Considerations from the Perspective of the EU’s Legal System. European Journal of Migration and Law. 2019;21(1):83– 116. doi:10.1163/15718166-12340043.</ref><ref>[12] Rosenblum MR, Tichenor DJ. The Oxford Handbook of the Pol- itics of International Migration. Oxford University Press; 2012. doi:10.1093/oxfordhb/9780195337228.013.0001.</ref><ref>[13] El-Enany N. The ‘New Europe’ and the ‘European Refugee’: The Subversion of the European Union’s Refugee Law by its Migration Policy. In: Juss SS, editor. The Ashgate Research Companion to Migration Law, Theory and Policy. 21. Routledge; 2013. pp. 3–24. doi:10.4324/9781315613239.</ref><ref>[14] Bowling B. Epilogue: The Borders of Punishment: To- wards a Criminology of Mobility. In: The Borders of Punishment. Oxford University Press; 2013. pp. 291–306. doi:10.1093/acprof:oso/9780199669394.003.0017.</ref><ref>[15] Heath Wellman C, Cole P. Debating the Ethics of Immigration. Oxford University Press; 2011. doi:10.1093/acprof:osobl/9780199731732.001.0001.</ref><ref>[16] Vigneswaran D. Territory, Migration and the Evolution of the International System. Palgrave Macmillan UK; 2013. doi:10.1057/9780230391291. The author also points out to a very interesting term “territoriality”, which is defined as “strategies that affect, influence or control people, phenomena and relationships, by delimiting and asserting control over a geographic area”.</ref><ref>[17] Stevens D. The Humaneness of EU Asylum Law and Policy. In: Ferreira N, Kostakopoulou D, editors. The Human Face of the Eu- ropean Union. Cambridge University Press; 2018. pp. 235–259. doi:10.1017/cbo9781139924795.011.</ref><ref>[18] Miller D. Strangers in Our Midst. Harvard University Press; 2018. doi:10.4159/9780674969827.</ref><ref>[19] de Bruycker P. Elements for a New European Consensus on Migra- tion and Asylum. In: de Bruycker P, de Somer M, editors. Towards a New European Consensus on Migration; 2019. pp. 145–159. Available from: https://odysseus-network.eu/from-tampere-20-to- tampere-2-0-towards-a-new-european-consensus-on-migration/.</ref><ref>[20] The author also adds the following: common funding and common positioning towards third countries.</ref><ref>[21] Haddad E. The Refugee in International Society: Be- tween Sovereigns. Cambridge University Press; 2008. doi:10.1017/CBO9780511491351.</ref><ref>[22] Grey C. Justice and Authority in Immigration Law. Bloomsbury Publishing. 2017; Available from: https: //www.bloomsburyprofessional.com/uk/justice-and-authority- in-immigration-law-9781509915446/.</ref><ref>[23] Kosińska AM. Prawa kulturalne obywateli państw trze- cich w prawie Unii Europejskiej. 2018; Available from: https://books-box.com/katalog/wydawnictwo-kul-katolickiego- uniwersytetu-lubelskiego/prawa-kulturalne-obywateli-panstw- trzecich-w-prawie-unii-europejskiej. As the author explains: “The living together principle, which the European Court of Human Rights referred to in a famous ruling in the case of S.A.S., presumes a restriction of the rights of an individual as an element of protection of the rights and freedoms of others, facilitating a harmonious social co-existence within the framework of civil society”.</ref><ref>[24] Trispiotis I. Two Interpretations of “Living Together”. In: European Human Rights Law. vol. 75. Cambridge University Press (CUP); 2016. pp. 580–607. doi:10.1017/s0008197316000568.</ref><ref>[25] Judgement of the European Court of Human Rights of 1 July 2014 in the case of S.A.S. v. France, complaint no. 43835/11. Strasbourg, France: European Court of Human Rights; 2014. Available from: http://hudoc.echr.coe.int/eng?i=001-145466.</ref><ref>[26] Carens J. The Ethics of Immigration. Oxford University Press; 2013.</ref><ref>[27] Pajnik M. 2016;pp. 239–257.</ref><ref>[28] Okólski M. Transition from Emigration to Immigration. In: Euro- pean Immigrations. Amsterdam University Press; 2012. pp. 23–44. doi:10.1515/9789048517275-002.</ref><ref>[29] Barankiewicz T. Współczesne metody badania prawa - Barankiewicz Tomasz | Polona. Studia Prawnicze KUL. 2010;41(1). Available from: https://polona.pl/item/wspolczesne- 76 metody-badania-prawa,MjE3NjMzNzA/.</ref><ref>[30] Decreto-legge 4 ottobre 2018, n. 113, Disposizioni urgenti in ma- teria di protezione internazionale e immigrazione, sicurezza pub- blica, nonche’ misure per la funzionalita’ del Ministero dell’interno e l’organizzazione e il funzionamento dell’Agenzia nazionale per l’amministrazione e la destinazione dei beni sequestrati e confiscati alla criminalita’ organizzata;.</ref><ref>[31] Legge 1 dicembre 2018, n. 132, Conversione in legge, con mod- ificazioni, del decreto-legge 4 ottobre 2018, n. 113, recante dis- posizioni urgenti in materia di protezione internazionale e immi- grazione, sicurezza pubblica, nonche’ misure per la funzionalita’ del Ministero dell’interno e l’organizzazione e il funzionamento dell’Agenzia nazionale per l’amministrazione e la destinazione dei beni sequestrati e confiscati alla criminalita’ organizzata. Delega al Governo in materia di riordino dei ruoli e delle carriere del personale delle Forze di polizia e delle Forze armate;.</ref><ref>[32] See, for instance: https://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/jun/13/ lega-nord-migrants-rome-stand-off-luca-zaia.</ref><ref>[33] I problemi della ‘sicurezza’: l’impatto psicologico e psicosociale della legge 132/2018; Documento della Associazione Italiana di Psicologia. Associazione Italiana di Psicologia; Associazione per gli Studi Giuridici sull’Immigrazione; 2019. The doubts con- cerning the adopted solutions and the treatment of migrants as, per se (a priori) threats to the security of the state were ex- pressed by, among others. Available from: http://www.asgi.it/wp- content/uploads/2019/04/2019_AIP_psicologia_immigrazione.pdf.</ref><ref>[34] Benvenuti M. Il dito e la luna. La protezione delle esigenze di carattere umanitario degli stranieri prima e dopo il decreto Salvini. Diritto, Immigrazione e Cittadinanza. 2019;(1). Available from: https://www.dirittoimmigrazionecittadinanza.it/archivio-saggi- commenti/saggi/fascicolo-n-1-2019-1/345-il-dito-e-la-luna-la- protezione-delle-esigenze-di-carattere-umanitario-degli-stranieri- prima-e-dopo-il-decreto-salvini/file.</ref><ref>[35] Loprieno D. Il trattenimento dello straniero alla luce della l. n. 132 del 2018. Diritto, Immigrazione e Cittadinanza. 2019;(1). Available from: https://www.dirittoimmigrazionecittadinanza.it/archivio-saggi- commenti/saggi/fascicolo-n-1-2019-1/337-il-trattenimento-dello- straniero-alla-luce-della-l-n-132-del-2018.</ref><ref>[36] The doubts concerning the compatibility of such solutions with fundamental rights guaranteed in the EU were expressed by the European Fundamental Rights Agency (FRA).</ref><ref>[37] Beyond the Peak: Challenges Remain, but Migration Numbers Drop. Access to Asylum. Asylum, Migration and Borders. Annual Review. European Union Agency for Fundamental Rights (FRA); 2019. doi:10.2811/069603.</ref><ref>[38] Vita, febbraio 2019. Seicento psicoanalisti scrivono a Mattarella contro il Decreto Sicurezza. Società Psicoanalitica Italiana; 2019. The same was also expressed by Italian NGOs – among others, Societa Psicoanalitica Italiana – a petition against the decree was signed by 600 psychoanalysts.</ref><ref>[39] Migration and Home Affairs. Humanitarian Protection. European Commission. In Germany, the idea of granting “permits on human- itarian grounds” is close to the one which functioned before the adoption of the Salvini decree. Available from: https://ec.europa.eu/ home-affairs/pages/glossary/humanitarian-protection_en.</ref><ref>[40] What is interesting, the objection of non-constitutionality concerns legal changes facilitating the revocation of Italian nationality in the case of committing terrorist offences, which, in the opinion of C. Corsi, leads to the breach of the constitutional principle of equality of citizens and the introduction of the new status civile. It remains an open question in the discussion whether the changes adopted in Italy are meant to counteract the return of militants.</ref><ref>[41] Corsi C. Evaluating the “Salvini Decree”: Doubts of Constitutional Legitimacy. Policy Briefs. 2019;(6). doi:10.2870/199546.</ref><ref>[42] Constituzione della Repubblica Italiana. Gazzetta Ufficiale della Repubblica Italiana. 1947;(298). Available from: https://www. gazzettaufficiale.it/anteprima/codici/costituzione. In accordance with Art. 10 of the Constitution of the Italian Republic: “The Ital- ian legal system conforms to the generally recognized principles of international law. The legal status of foreigners is regulated by law in conformity with international provisions and treaties”.</ref><ref>[43] Forsythe DP. Humanitarian Protection: The International Com- mittee of the Red Cross and the United Nations High Commis- sioner for Refugees. 2001;83(843):675–697. Available from: https: //www.icrc.org/en/doc/assets/files/other/675_698_forsythe.pdf.</ref><ref>[44] See, for instance: Judgement of the ECtHR of 15.12.2016 in the case of Khlaiffia and Others v. Italy, application no. 16483/12, Judge- ment of the ECtHR of 16.11.2016, Hirsii Jamaa and Others v. Italy, application no. 27765/09.</ref><ref>[45] Non-refoulement as a Principle of International Law and the Role of the Judiciary in its Implementation, Dialogue between judges 2017, Council of Europe 2017. European Court of Human Rights; 2017. Available from: www.echr.coe.int.</ref><ref>[46] It concerns the reintroduction of the maximum period of detention, which in accordance with the EU law lasts 180 days, in place of the 90-day pre-removal detention period established in 2012.</ref><ref>[47] Italy Immigration Detention Profile, January 2018, 6. Global De- tention Project;. Available from: https://www.globaldetentionproject. org/.</ref><ref>[48] What is significant, the report states that “According to the Senate Extraordinary Commission for the Promotion of Human Rights, the average detention period in Italy’s long-term detention centers dur- ing 2015 was 25.5 days.” (p. 7). In view of the above, it is even more difficult to understand the reversal of the positively-regarded reform of the Turco-Napolitano Act.</ref><ref>[49] Case of Tarakhel v. Switzerland. European Court of Human Rights; 2014. 29217/12. Available from: https://www.asylumlawdatabase.eu/en/content/ecthr-tarakhel- v-switzerland-application-no-2921712.</ref><ref>[50] Country Report Italy, Asylum Information Database (AIDA), FRA, Italy 2018. Asylum Information Database (AIDA); 2018. Available from: https://www.asylumineurope.org/reports/country/italy.</ref><ref>[51] Decreto-legge 14 giugno 2019, n. 53. Disposizioni urgenti in materia di ordine e sicurezza pubblica. (19G00063) (GU n.138 del 14-6- 2019). Gazzetta Ufficiale della Repubblica Italiana. 2019; Available from: https://www.gazzettaufficiale.it/eli/id/2019/06/14/19G00063/ sg.</ref><ref>[52] Legge 8 agosto 2019, n. 77. Conversione in legge, con mod- ificazioni, del decreto-legge 14 giugno 2019, n. 53, recante disposizioni urgenti in materia di ordine e sicurezza pubblica. (19G00089) (GU Serie Generale n.186 del 09-08-2019). Gazzetta Ufficiale della Repubblica Italiana. 2019; Available from: https: //www.gazzettaufficiale.it/eli/id/2019/08/09/19G00089/sg.</ref><ref>[53] Il DL. n. 53/2019, convertito, con modificazioni, nella L. n. 77 /2019 Analisi critica del c.d. “Decreto sicurezza bis” relativamente alle disposizioni inerenti il diritto dell’immigrazione, 13 settembre 2019. Assocciazione per gli Studi Guridici sul’ Immigrazione (ASGI). 2019; Available from: https://www.asgi.it/notizie/decreto-sicurezza-bis- lanalisi-dellasgi/.</ref><ref>[54] Ministero degli affari esteri e della cooperazione internazionale. De- creto 4 ottobre 2019. Individuazione dei Paesi di origine sicuri, ai sensi dell’articolo 2-bis del decreto legislativo 28 gennaio 2008, n. 25. (19A06239) (GU Serie Generale n.235 del 07-10-2019). Gazzetta Ufficiale della Repubblica Italiana. 2019; Available from: https://www.gazzettaufficiale.it/eli/id/2019/10/07/19A06239/sg.</ref><ref>[55] Nota di commento del decreto del ministro degli affari esteri e della cooperazione internazionale 4 ottobre 2019 sull’elenco dei paesi di origine sicuri (27 Novembre 2019). Assocciazione per gli Studi Guridici sul’ Immigrazione (ASGI). 2019; Available from: http: //www.asgi.it/wp-content/uploads/2019/11/Nota-ASGI-commento- d.M.A.E.-4-10-2019-paesi-sicuri-definitivo-27-11-2019.docx.pdf.</ref><ref>[56] Migration: Key Fundamental Rights Concerns, FRA, 1.04.2019- 30.06.2019. European Union Agency for Fundamental Rights (FRA); 2019. 4. Available from: www.fra.europa.eu.</ref><ref>[57] ‘We can do this!’—Merkel’s Famous Words Five Years on after Refugee Influx to Germany. Made for Minds. 2021; Available from: https://www.dw.com/en/merkel-germany-refugees/a-54769229.</ref><ref>[58] Migration, Asylum and Refugees in Germany: Understand- ing the Data. Data Briefing Series. 2016;(1). Available from: https://www.iom.int/sites/default/files/country/docs/Germany/ Germany-Data-Briefing-1Jan2016.pdf.</ref><ref>[59] Bundesministerium des Innern, für Bau und Heimat. Available from: https://www.bmi.bund.de/SharedDocs/pressemitteilungen/DE/ 2019/08/geg-geordnete-rueckkehr-gesetz.html. 77</ref><ref>[60] The circumstances which do not constitute an excessive burden on the foreign national are believed to be, in accordance with paragraph 60(3), the following: cooperation in the issuing and extending of the validity of the passport in accordance with the regulations of the German passport law, personal appearance before the agencies of the country of origin; submitting a statement, before the agencies of the country of origin, on voluntary leaving the federal territory; pay all the fees as defined in the country of origin and applicable under official institutional activities regarding the issuing of a pass- port; submit another application for a new passport or a document replacing the passport.</ref><ref>[61] In accordance with par. 62(3): By the order of the court, a foreigner is placed in custody (preventive custody) in order to safeguard the possibility of expelling him from the country, if: 1. there is a risk that he/she may abscond, 2. on the grounds of unlawful entry into the country the foreigner is obliged to leave its territory in a feasible way or 3. an order was issued to expel a foreigner from the country in accordance with § 58a, which, however, cannot be executed with immediate effect”.</ref><ref>[62] Such official detention may take place when: 1. there is a high probability that there exist the reasons defined in paragraph 1(1); 2. there is no possibility of obtaining a court ruling on the matter of ordering a detention with a view to expelling the foreigner from the country in the understanding of paragraph 1, and 3. There is a justified reason to believe that the foreigner will avoid the execution of the order to detain him with a view of expelling him/her from the country”.</ref><ref>[63] Drittes Gesetz zur Änderung des Asylbewerberleistungsgesetzes. Bundesanzeiger Verlag. 2019;18(BGBl. I 2019 no. 31S.1290). Available from: https://www.bgbl.de/xaver/bgbl/start.xav#__bgbl_ _%2F%2F*%5B%40attr_id%3D%27bgbl119s1290.pdf%27%5D_ _1584310711114.</ref><ref>[64] Zweites Gesetz zur Verbesserung der Registrierung und des Date- naustausches zu aufenthalts- und asylrechtlichen Zwecken (Zweites Datenaustauschverbesserungsgesetz - 2. DAVG). Bundesanzeiger Verlag. 2019;4(BGBl. I 2019 no. 29 S. 1131). Available from: https: //www.bgbl.de/xaver/bgbl/start.xav#__bgbl__%2F%2F*%5B% 40attr_id%3D%27bgbl119s1290.pdf%27%5D__1584316059056.</ref><ref>[65] Verordnung zur Änderung der Verordnung zum Integrationsge- setz und Beschäftigungsverordnung. Bundesanzeiger Verlag. 2019;22(BGBl. I 2019 no. 28 S. 1109). Available from: https: //www.bgbl.de/xaver/bgbl/start.xav#__bgbl__%2F%2F*%5B% 40attr_id%3D%27bgbl119s1109.pdf%27%5D__1565356605528.</ref><ref>[66] As the European Agency for Fundamental Rights observes, the act “abolishes the so-called ‘priority check’ (Vorrangprüfung), pre- viously required before granting an employment permit to asylum applicants who have resided in Germany for three months or longer. The priority check assessed whether a German national would be available for the job before it was offered to an asylum applicant”.</ref><ref>[67] Migration: Key Fundamental Rights Concerns, FRA, 1.07.2019- 30.09.2019. European Union Agency for Fundamental Rights (FRA); 2019. 8. Available from: www.fra.europa.eu.</ref><ref>[68] Act on Foreigners of December 12, 2013, Journal of Laws 2020.35; Act on granting protection to foreigners within the territory of the Republic of Poland of June 13, 2003, Journal of Laws 2019.1666. With regard to the issues related to migration security, Art. 144a was added to the Act on foreigners in 2019 which allows the Minister competent for internal affairs to issue decisions on the prohibition of enrolling a foreigner to a higher education course when “it is required for the reasons of defence or the security of the country or for safeguarding the security of the state and public order” (Art. 144a(1)(1)).</ref><ref>[69] See Art. 39(1)(3-5) of the Act on granting protection to foreigners on the territory of the Republic of Poland.</ref><ref>[70] See: Judgment of the Court, 31 January 2013, H. I. D. and B. A. v Refugee Applications Commissioner and Others, C 175/11, ECLI:EU:C:2013:45.</ref><ref>[71] Tribunale di Genova, Sezione XI Civile, Decreto n. cronologico 96/2020, 10.01.2020. European Database of Asylum Law; 2020. Available from: https://www.asylumlawdatabase.eu/en/content/italy- well-founded-risk-inhuman-treatment-case-return-nigeria.</ref><ref>[72] Protezione sussidiaria a richiedente asilo nigeriana: il racconto presenta fortissimi indicatori che portano a ritenere che la stessa - benché non lo dichiari apertamente - sia stata vittima di tratta. 2020; Available from: https://www.meltingpot.org/Protezione-sussidiaria- a-richiedente-asilo-nigeriana-il.html#.Xzr3Cadxc2z.</ref><ref>[73] La Corte di Appello di Bologna. Prima Sezione Civile, Sentenza n. 192/2020 pubbl. il 14/01/2020RG. Repubblica Italiana; 2020. Available from: https://www.meltingpot.org/IMG/pdf/corte_appello_ bo_sent._192_del_14.01.2020_ucraina__integrazione_legami_ familiari_in_italia_umanitaria.pdf.</ref><ref>[74] Italy: Recognition of Humanitarian Protection due to the Deterioration of the Quality of Life in Ukraine. Euro- pean Database of Asylum Law; 2020. Available from: https://www.asylumlawdatabase.eu/en/content/italy-recognition- humanitarian-protection-due-deterioration-quality-life-ukraine.</ref><ref>[75] Italy – Administrative Tribunal Declares Decision to Withdraw Recep- tion Provisions Unlawful. European Database of Asylum Law; 2018. Available from: https://www.asylumlawdatabase.eu/en/content/italy- %E2%80%93-administrative-tribunal-declares-decision-withdraw- reception-provisions-unlawful.</ref><ref>[76] Italy: Recognition of the Right to Enter as Compensation for Illegiti- mate Collective Expulsions to Libya by the Italian Coast Guard in 2009. European Database of Asylum Law; 2019. Available from: https://www.asylumlawdatabase.eu/en/content/italy-recognition- right-enter-compensation-illegitimate-collective-expulsions-libya- italian.</ref><ref>[77] Italy-Libya Connection. Human Rights Watch. 2009 Sep 23; Available from: https://www.hrw.org/news/2009/09/23/italy-libya- connection.</ref><ref>[78] Libya: Renewal of Migration Deal Confirms Italy’s Complicity in Tor- ture of Migrants and Refugees. Amnesty International; 2020. Avail- able from: https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/news/2020/01/libya- renewal-of-migration-deal-confirms-italys-complicity-in-torture-of- migrants-and-refugees/.</ref><ref>[79] Commissioner Calls on the Italian Government to Suspend the Co-operation Activities in Place with the Libyan Coast Guard that Impact on the Return of Persons Intercepted at Sea to Libya. Council of Europe; 2020. Available from: https://www.coe.int/en/web/commissioner/-/ommissioner-calls-on- the-italian-government-to-suspend-the-co-operation-activities-in- place-with-the-libyan-coast-guard-that-impact-on-the-return-of- p.</ref><ref>[80] Judgement of the CJEU of 21.04.2017 in the case of X and X v. Etat belge, C 638/16 PPU, ECLI:EU:C:2017:173.</ref><ref>[81] Migrant Integration not Enough for Stay Permit - Court. ANSA, Latest News; 2019. Available from: https://www.ansa.it/english/ news/2019/11/13/migrant-integration-not-enough-for-stay-permit- court_c7e0d4ae-72cb-496d-a472-bea3bae7c7f3.html.</ref><ref>[82] Humanitarian Protection, EMN Glossary. Available from: https://ec.europa.eu/home-affairs/what-wedo/networks/european_ migration_network/glossary_search/humanitarian-protection_en.</ref><ref>[83] Positive Premises to Grant the Residence Permit for Hu- manitarian Reasons. Urz ˛ ad do Spraw Cudzoziemców. 2020; Available from: https://udsc.gov.pl/en/cudzoziemcy/obywatele- panstw-trzecich/zobowiazanie-do-powrotu/przeslanki-negatywne- zobowiazania-cudzoziemca-do-powrotu/zgoda-na-pobyt-ze- wzgledow-humanitarnych/przeslanki-pozytywne-do-udzielenia- zgody-na-pobyt-ze-wzgledow-humanitarnych/.</ref><ref>[84] La sentenza di Corte Suprema do Cassazione n. 29460/2019. Associazione per gli Studi Giuridici sull’Immigrazione (ASGI). 2019 Sep 24; Available from: https://www.asgi.it/asilo-eprotezione- internazionale/cassazione-decreto-sicurezza/.</ref><ref>[85] Corte di Cassazione, ordinanza n. 24388. European Database of Asylum Law. 2019 Sep 30; Available from: https://www.asylumlawdatabase.eu/en/content/italy-court- must-provide-details-preliminary-assessment-real-risk-present- countries-origin.</ref><ref>[86] Sentenza di Corte Surema di Cassazione, causa 164/2018. European Database of Asylum Law. 2018 Jan 5; Available from: https://www.asylumlawdatabase.eu/en/content/italy-court- cassation-clarifies-scope-right-legal-aid-%E2%80%9Cirregular- 78 migrants%E2%80%9D.</ref><ref>[87] Decision of the ECHR in Case Rackete and Others v. Italy, applica- tion no. 32969/19; Available from: https://www.hudoc.echr.coe.int. The Court decides not to indicate an interim measure requiring that the applicants be authorized to disembark in Italy from the ship Sea-Watch 3.</ref><ref>[88] Italy: Preliminary Judge of the Court of Agrigento clears Sea Watch 3 Captain of Charges. European Database of Asylum Law. 2019; Available from: https://www.asylumlawdatabase.eu/en/content/italy- preliminary-judge-court-agrigento-clears-sea-watch-3-captain- charges.</ref><ref>[89] Decreto Legislativo 25 luglio 1998, n. 286, Testo unico delle dis- posizioni concernenti la disciplina dell’immigrazione e norme sulla condizione dello straniero, pubblicato nella Gazzetta Ufficiale n. 191 del 18 agosto 1998 - Supplemento Ordinario n. 139. In accor- dance with Art. 10(4): “Le disposizioni dei commi 1, 2 e 3 e quelle dell’articolo 4, commi 3 e 6, non si applicano nei casi previsti dalle disposizioni vigenti che disciplinano l’asilo politico, il riconoscimento dello status di rifugiato, ovvero l’adozione di misure di protezione temporanea per motivi umanitari” (The provisions laid down in para- graphs 1, 2 and 3 and those of Art. 4(3)(6) are not applicable in the situations laid down in the existing regulations, which govern the is- sues related to political asylum, the granting of refugee status or the adoption of interim measures for humanitarian reasons). Available from: https://www.camera.it/parlam/leggi/deleghe/98286dl.htm.</ref><ref>[90] Regulation (EU) no. 604/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council of June 26, 2013 Establishing the Criteria and Mecha- nisms for Determining the Member State Responsible for Examining an Application for International Protection Lodged in one of the Member States by a Third-country National or a Stateless Person. Official Journal of the European Union. 2013;(L 180/31). Avail- able from: https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/PDF/ ?uri=CELEX:32013R0604&amp;from=EN.</ref><ref>[91] Judgement of the Higher Administrative Court of Düsseldorf, 8.05.2018, Case 8L5135/17A. Germany: Administrative Court of Dusseldorf quashes transfer of Syrian family to Romania. 2018; Available from: https://www.asylumlawdatabase.eu/en/content/ germany-administrative-court-dusseldorf-quashes-transfer- syrian-family-romania.</ref><ref>[92] Judgement of the European Court of Human Rights of 4.11.2014 r. in the case of Tarakhel v. Switzerland, Complaint no. 29217/12.</ref><ref>[93] Judgement of the Federal Administrative Court of Germany. 2018 Aug 20; Available from: https://www.asylumlawdatabase.eu/ en/content/germany-federal-administrative-court-rejects-bamf- appeal-regarding-returns-refugees-bulgaria.</ref><ref>[94] Judgement of the Augsburg Administrative Court. 2018 Nov 2; Avail- able from: https://www.asylumlawdatabase.eu/en/content/germany- %E2%80%93-augsburg-administrative-court-rules-case-dublin- transfer-pregnant-asylum-seeker.</ref><ref>[95] Judgement of the Administrative Court of Magdeburg. 2018 Nov 13; Available from: https://www.asylumlawdatabase.eu/en/ content/germany-%E2%80%93-magdeburg-court-suspends- return-beneficiary-international-protection-greece.</ref><ref>[96] Judgement of the Administrative Court of Munich. 2019 Aug 8; Avail- able from: https://www.asylumlawdatabase.eu/en/content/germany- administrative-court-munich-rules-against-provisional-return- syrian-applicant-greece.</ref><ref>[97] Germany – Regensburg Administrative Court Rules on Ab- sconding and time limits for Dublin Transfers. 2019; Available from: https://www.asylumlawdatabase.eu/en/content/germany- %E2%80%93-regensburg-administrative-court-rules-absconding- and-time-limits-dublin-transfers. Moving further, the administrative court of Regensburg in its judgement of 9 January 2019 provided interpretation of Art. 29(2) of the Dublin Regulation III.</ref><ref>[98] Judgement of the Berlin Administrative Court. 2018 Sep 4; Available from: https://www.asylumlawdatabase.eu/en/content/germany- %E2%80%93-berlin-administrative-court-rules-possibility-family- reunification-during-minor%E2%80%99s.</ref><ref>[99] Judgement of the Munster Administrative Court. 2018 Dec 22; Avail- able from: https://www.asylumlawdatabase.eu/en/content/germany- %E2%80%93-m%C3%BCnster-administrative-courtobliged- german-asylum-authorities-accept-delayed-take.</ref><ref>[100] Judgement of the Court of 13.11.2018 in the case of X and X v. Staatssecretaris van Veiligheid en Justitie, joined cases C 47/17 and C 48/17, ECLI:EU:C:2018:900.</ref><ref>[101] Act of 14 June 1960 Code of Administrative Procedure. Journal of Laws. 1960;(30). Available from: http://www.parliament.am/library/ varchakaniravaxaxtum19/lehastan.pdf.</ref><ref>[102] Białas J, Górczyńska M, Witko D. Dost˛ ep do procedury azylowej na zewn˛ etrznych granicach Polski Stan obecny i wyzwania na przyszłość. 2019; Available from: www.hfhr.pl.</ref><ref>[103] Art. 28 of the Act on foreigners concerns the refusal of entry into the territory of the Republic of Poland to a foreigner. In accordance with its paragraph 2(2), a decision refusing entry is not issued with regard to a foreigner, when he/she: a) declared an intention to submit an application for international protection in cases laid down in Art. 28(1) or Art. 6(1) of the Act of 13 June 2003 on granting protection to foreigners on the territory of the Republic of Poland b) submitted an application for international protection (...).</ref><ref>[104] Judgement of the Supreme Administrative Court, Ref. no. II OSK 345/18. 2018 Sep 20; Available from: http://orzeczenia.nsa.gov.pl/ doc/6422D006AE.</ref><ref>[105] Judgement of the Supreme Administrative Court of 20.09.2020, Ref. no. OSK 445/18. In accordance with the reasoning of the court: “As a rule, the statements of the person submitting a cassation complaint should be given credit, to the effect that such significant activities as questioning or interviewing a foreigner on the border should take place in the presence of his/her legal representative, if such had been appointed. However, the specificity of the proceed- ings requires assuming that such an obligation exists on the side of the administration only when the legal representative had already been appointed and is present at the moment of crossing the border, whereas the appointing of a legal representative does not have to entail the submission of the authorization documents”.</ref><ref>[106] Application no. 51246/17, D.A. and Others against Poland lodged on 20 July 2017. European Court of Human Rights; 2017. Available from: http://hudoc.echr.coe.int/eng?i=001-177298.</ref><ref>[107] Application no. 51246/17, D.A. and Others against Poland lodged on 20 July 2017. European Court of Human Rights; 2017. Available from: http://hudoc.echr.coe.int/eng?i=001-176484.</ref><ref>[108] A Visit to the Railway Border Crossing in Terespol. Rzecznik Praw Obywatelskich. 2019; Available from: https://bip.brpo.gov.pl/pl/content/wizytacja-kolejowego-przejscia- granicznego-w-terespolu-wrzesien-2019.</ref><ref>[109] Act of July 15, 1987 on the Ombudsman. Journal of Laws 2020627 of 20200408;See: Art. 13 and the following.</ref><ref>[110] Judgement of the Supreme Administrative Court of 18.12.2019, Ref. no. OSK 2219/19.</ref><ref>[111] Rzecznik Praw Obywatelskich. Available from: https://www. rpo.gov.pl/pl/content/nsa-uwzglednil-argumenty-rpo-w-sprawie- nieprzyznania-ochronymiedzynarodowej-obywatelowi-rosji/.</ref><ref>[112] Judgement of the Supreme Administrative Court of 19.09.2019, Ref. no. OSK 1849/19.</ref><ref>[113] Judgement of the European Court of Human Rights of 10 April 2018 in the case of Bistieva and others v. Poland, application no. 75157/14.</ref><ref>[114] Helsińska Fundacja Praw Człowieka. Available from: https://www.hfhr.pl/detencja-dzieci-cudzoziemcow-w-polsc.ehfpc- kieruje-wystapienie-do-specjalnego-sprawozdawcy-onz/.</ref></root>