<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMed 2.0//EN" "http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov:80/entrez/query/static/PubMed.dtd">
<ArticleSet><Article><Journal><PublisherName>Librello</PublisherName><JournalTitle>Challenges in Sustainability</JournalTitle><Issn>2297-6477</Issn><Volume>4</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate PubStatus="epublish"><Year>2016</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>25</Day></PubDate></Journal><ArticleTitle>Building Urban Agricultural Commons: A Utopia or a Reality?</ArticleTitle><FirstPage>3</FirstPage><LastPage>9</LastPage><ELocationID EIdType="doi">10.12924/cis2016.04010003</ELocationID><Language>EN</Language><AuthorList><Author><FirstName>Pierre</FirstName><LastName>Donadieu</LastName><Affiliation>National School of Landscape Architecture of Versailles, Versailles, France. p.donadieu@versailles.ecole-paysage.fr</Affiliation></Author></AuthorList><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pii">cis-4.1.3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><History><PubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2016</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>29</Day></PubDate><PubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2016</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>22</Day></PubDate></History><Abstract>There are several categories of urban agriculture which need to be distinguished if we want to efficiently feed urban inhabitants with local agricultural produce while benefiting from other functions filled by urban agricultural landscapes: namely, eco-systemic functions or ecological and social functions. The second function will focus on methods to regulate unbuilt land in urban areas which have virtually no regulations and others which have strict controls preventing construction. The last will consist of possibilities to build, what I would refer to as, urban agricultural commons: in other words, tangible and intangible resources produced with farmers and gardeners for the inhabitants; for their local consumption and for the quality of the living environment, based on a political principle for common action. The concept of common is derived from the works of socioeconomist E. Ostrom (1990; [1]) and French philosophers P. Dardot et C. Laval (2014; [2]): “What is built in common”. It was applied to urban agriculture and landscape (Donadieu, 2012, 2014; [3,4]). The concept of urban agriculture has been used worldwide in the last twenty years by researchers, especially in France by A. Fleury (2005; [5]) and P. Donadieu(1998; [6]), in Mediterranean regions (Nasr and Padilla, 2004; [7]), in Asia, Africa and North and South America—all through the publications of the Resource Centres Urban Agriculture &amp;amp; Food Security (RUAF; [8]).</Abstract></Article></ArticleSet>
