<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMed 2.0//EN" "http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov:80/entrez/query/static/PubMed.dtd">
<ArticleSet><Article><Journal><PublisherName>Librello</PublisherName><JournalTitle>Challenges in Sustainability</JournalTitle><Issn>2297-6477</Issn><Volume>3</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate PubStatus="epublish"><Year>2015</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>03</Day></PubDate></Journal><ArticleTitle>Time for Decarbonization of Conservation and Development Projects? The Political Ecology of Carbon Projects</ArticleTitle><FirstPage>16</FirstPage><LastPage>17</LastPage><ELocationID EIdType="doi">10.12924/cis2015.03010016</ELocationID><Language>EN</Language><AuthorList><Author><FirstName>Pierre</FirstName><MiddleName>L.</MiddleName><LastName>Ibisch</LastName><Affiliation>Centre for Econics and Ecosystem Management, Eberswalde University for Sustainable Development, Germany. pierre.ibisch@hnee.de</Affiliation></Author></AuthorList><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pii">cis-3.1.16</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><History><PubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2015</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day></PubDate><PubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2015</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>26</Day></PubDate></History><Abstract>The globe's first carbon projects were designed and implemented approximately 20 years ago following scientific insights that emissions of greenhouse gases needed to be mitigated. Visible in some of these early projects were the important aspects of social governance and local benefit sharing. The projects promised to be a panacea to environmental, social and economic problems in remote rural areas of developing countries. However, it took another decade before a wave of hundreds of carbon projects were launched. Many of the projects were offered under the mechanism of REDD+ (Reducing Emissions from Deforestation and forest Degradation, plus the role of conservation, sustainable forest management and carbon enhancement), as well as under a variety of voluntary schemes and national programs, public-private partnerships, and forestry-based investment initiatives. As decision-makers prepare the Conference of the Parties of the United Nations Framework Convention on Climatic Change in Paris (COP21), Earthscan has released a book entitled `Carbon conflicts and forest landscapes in Africa', edited by Melissa Leach and Ian Scoones. According to the editors, the focus of the book is on what happens on the ground when carbon forestry projects arrive, what types of projects work, and, equally important, what doesn’t work.</Abstract></Article></ArticleSet>
