<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="research-article"
         dtd-version="3.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">of</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title xml:lang="en">Organic Farming</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">2297-6485</issn>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Librello</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12924/of2018.04010001</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Editorial</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Research into Practice—Promoting Participation, Perseverance and Publications</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <name>
                  <surname>Döring</surname>
                  <given-names>Thomas</given-names>
               </name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">1</xref>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">2</xref>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <aff id="A2">
            <label>1</label>Editor-in-Chief of Organic Farming, Librello, Basel, Switzerland</aff>
         <aff id="A3">
            <label>2</label>Agroecology and Organic Farming Group, University of Bonn, Bonn, Germany</aff>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <day>16</day>
            <month>05</month>
            <year>2018</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>4</volume>
         <issue>1</issue>
         <fpage>1</fpage>
         <lpage>2</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-year>2005</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <abstract>
            <p>This year, organic farmers, advisors and researchers in the West of Germany celebrate the 25th anniversary of the foundation of an organic research and demonstration network. Established to support and improve organic farming systems, the network is funded by the federal state of North Rhine-Westphalia and is organized around 30 participating pilot farms called Leitbetriebe (‘leading farms’), with support from the university of Bonn and the Chamber of Agriculture For each of the practice-oriented research topics covered in this network, the typical five-year cycle of research involves a first year of experimental exploration and literature studies. The farmers participating in the pilot farm project discuss and select the topics of priority and review the research plans proposed by the scientists. This is followed by three years of systematic replicated field trials on several farms, and a final year of demonstration and evaluation, where the presentation of results is jointly done by farmers and researchers.</p>
         </abstract>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd>organic agriculture, participatory research</kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>This year, organic farmers, advisors and researchers in the West of Germany celebrate the 25th anniversary of the foundation of an organic research and demonstration network. Established to support and improve organic farming systems, the network is funded by the federal state of North Rhine-Westphalia and is organized around 30 participating pilot farms called Leitbetriebe (‘leading farms’), with support from the university of Bonn and the Chamber of Agriculture [<xref rid="R01" ref-type="bibr">R01</xref>]. For each of the practice-oriented research topics covered in this network, the typical five-year cycle of research involves a first year of experimental exploration and literature studies. The farmers participating in the pilot farm project discuss and select the topics of priority and review the research plans proposed by the scientists. This is followed by three years of systematic replicated field trials on several farms, and a final year of demonstration and evaluation, where the presentation of results is jointly done by farmers and researchers. The topics studied over the last quarter of a century include pre-sprouting of potatoes [<xref rid="R02" ref-type="bibr">R02</xref>], undersowing [<xref rid="R03" ref-type="bibr">R03</xref>], fertilization of in oil seed rape [<xref rid="R04" ref-type="bibr">R04</xref>], species mixtures in pasture systems [<xref rid="R05" ref-type="bibr">R05</xref>], strategies to reduce nitrogen losses [<xref rid="R06" ref-type="bibr">R06</xref>], the cut-and-carry system [<xref rid="R07" ref-type="bibr">R07</xref>], and several more. The participating farms are selected to represent the wide range of environmental conditions within North Rhine Westphalia, where according to the most recent figures nearly 2,000 certified organic farms operated on 78,000 ha of agricultural land [<xref rid="R08" ref-type="bibr">R08</xref>].</p>
      
      <p>The experience gained over the past 25 years in this organic research and demonstration network confirms and complements the insights obtained in similar operations elsewhere [<xref rid="R09" ref-type="bibr">R09</xref>]. To be successful, integrative partnerships between research and organic practitioners require perseverance, patience, and reliable funding. In particular, the period of three years that research projects are usually funded for is far too short to establish the trust and mutual understanding necessary for successful implementation of research. Innovations developed in agricultural research just take a long time to be established in practice.</p>
         <p>Further, adoption depends on individual advice adapting recommendations for the complexity of individual organic farming systems. In fact, the grassland research within the pilot farm project has highlighted the need to individualize recommendations, partly because of the tremendous effects of interactions between species and genotypes of crops, pasture management and environment. Wider adoption of research also requires a critical mass of farmers acting as innovators, which is more difficult to achieve in the organic sector. Finally, implementation and adoption of research-powered innovations requires continuous dialogue between researchers, advisors and farmers, based on a common language, jointly identified research questions, and active knowledge transfer delivering clear, brief and targeted outputs.</p>
         <p>As experience in the pilot farm project has also shown, knowledge transfer in the form of publishing in international peer-reviewed journals is not a necessary requirement for the adoption of research in practice. In fact, international publishing is often not seen as belonging to the culture of participatory research in agriculture. However, it acts as an indispensable tool for quality control within science. It also helps to increase visibility for innovations in organic agriculture on the international stage, thereby generating wider feedback. Within a regional farmer-led research network, however, publishing internationally is typically not high on the agenda, despite the great potential to do so, and despite the gains expected from sharing experiences with an international audience. Conversely, practice oriented research is not always appreciated in the academic world.
            </p>
      
      
      <p>At its inception, this journal pledged to bridge this gap between practice and research for organic farming [<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">R10</xref>]. As one of the means to achieve this, the open access publishing model of Organic Farming has so far generated several thousands of free downloads per issue, thereby promoting the visibility and impact of the published research. Further, this journal will continue to encourage submissions at the interface of organic practice and research, with article formats beyond traditional structures. Finally, an updated and more flexible system is being implemented for publication fees, which includes a post-acceptance fee in addition to the membership model, thereby opening the journal to a wider range of authors.</p>
      
   </body>
   <back>
      <ref-list>
         <ref id="R01">
            <element-citation publication-type="confproc" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Stumm</surname>
                     <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Köpke</surname>
                     <given-names>U.</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <article-title>Organic Pilot Farms in North Rhine-Westphalia (Germany)</article-title>
               <source>16th IFOAM Organic World Congress, Modena</source>
               <year>2008</year>
               <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Neuhoff</surname>
                     <given-names>D and Halberg, N and Alföldi, T and Lockeretz, W and Thommen, A and Rasmussen, I.A and Hermansen, J and Vaarst, M and Lück, L and Carporali, F and Jensen, H and Migliorini, P and Willer, H</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <conf-loc>Modena, Italy</conf-loc>
               <month>June 16-20</month>
               <conf-sponsor>Research Institute of Organic Agriculture FiBL</conf-sponsor>
                                
               <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                         xlink:href="http://orgprints.org/12594"
                         xlink:type="simple">http://orgprints.org/12594</ext-link>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="R02">
            <element-citation publication-type="confproc" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Stumm</surname>
                     <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Köpke</surname>
                     <given-names>U</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <article-title>Einfluss von Lichtspektrum und Beleuchtungsstärke auf das Keimlängenwachstum und den Ertrag von Kartoffeln</article-title>
               <source>11. Wissenschaftstagung Ökologischer Landbau</source>
               <year>2011</year>
               <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Leithold</surname>
                     <given-names>G and Becker, K and Brock, C and Fischinger, S and Spiegel, A K and, Spory, K and Wilbois, K. P and Williges, U</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <conf-loc>Gießen, Germany</conf-loc>
               <month>March 16-18</month>
               <publisher-name>Verlag Dr. Köster</publisher-name>
               <fpage>262</fpage>
               <lpage>265</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="R03">
            <element-citation publication-type="confproc" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Stumm</surname>
                     <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Köpke</surname>
                     <given-names>U</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <article-title>Untersaaten in Kartoffeln zur Reduzierung der Spätverunkrautung</article-title>
               <source>9. Wissenschaftstagung Ökologischer Landbau</source>
               <year>2007</year>
               <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Zikeli</surname>
                     <given-names>S and Claupein, W and Dabbert, S and Kaufmann, B and Müller, T and Valle Zárate</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <conf-loc>Hohenheim, Germany</conf-loc>
               <month>\hlDate?</month>
               <conf-name>Universität Hohenheim</conf-name>
               <fpage>117</fpage>
               <lpage>120</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="R04">
            <element-citation publication-type="confproc" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Stumm</surname>
                     <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Berg</surname>
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Köpke</surname>
                     <given-names>U</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <article-title>Anbau und Düngung von Winterraps (\textitBrassica napus L.) im Ökologischen Landbau, in Werte —Wege—Wirkungen: Biolandbau im Spannungsfeld zwischen Ernährungssicherung, Markt und Klimawandel</article-title>
               <source>10. Wissenschaftstagung Ökologischer Landbau</source>
               <year>2009</year>
               <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Mayer J, et al.</surname>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <volume>Band 1: Boden, Pflanzenbau, Agrartechnik, Umwelt- und Naturschutz, Biolandbau international, Wissensmanagement</volume>
               <conf-loc>Zürich, Switzerland</conf-loc>
               <month>\hlDate?</month>
               <conf-name>ETH Zürich</conf-name>
               <publisher-name>Verlag Dr. Köster</publisher-name>
               <fpage>193</fpage>
               <lpage>196</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="R05">
            <element-citation publication-type="confproc" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Leisen</surname>
                     <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Vollmer</surname>
                     <given-names>B</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Gutberlet</surname>
                     <given-names>K</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>König</surname>
                     <given-names>M E.</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <article-title>Test von Kleegras-Kräuter-Mischungen in Öko - Milchviehbetrieben</article-title>
               <source>13. Wissenschaftstagung Ökologischer Landbau</source>
               <year>2015</year>
               <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Häring</surname>
                     <given-names>A.M and Hörning, B and Hoffmann-Bahnsen, R and Luley, H and Luthardt, V and Pape, J and Trei, G</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <conf-loc>Eberswalde, Germany</conf-loc>
               <fpage>419</fpage>
               <lpage>422</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="R06">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Berg</surname>
                     <given-names>M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Haas</surname>
                     <given-names>G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Leisen</surname>
                     <given-names>E</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Schenke</surname>
                     <given-names>H</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <article-title>Stickstoffmanagement im ökologisch wirtschaftenden Betrieb: Minderung von Stickstoffverlusten: Dokumentation 10 Jahre Leitbetriebe Ökologischer Landbau in Nordrhein-Westfalen</article-title>
               <source>Schriftenreihe des Lehr- und Forschungsschwerpunktes ``Umweltverträgliche und Standortgerechte Landwirtschaft''</source>
               <year>2003</year>
               <volume>105</volume>
               <fpage>64</fpage>
               <lpage>75</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="R07">
            <element-citation publication-type="confproc" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Stumm</surname>
                     <given-names>C</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Köpke</surname>
                     <given-names>U.</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <article-title>Düngung mit Sprossmasse von Futterleguminosen: Lachgasemissionen und Nitratverluste</article-title>
               <source>14. Wissenschaftstagung Ökologischer Landbau, Campus Weihenstephan, Freising-Weihenstephan</source>
               <year>2017</year>
               <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Wolfrum</surname>
                     <given-names>S and Heuwinkel, H and Reents, H.H.</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <conf-loc>Freising-Weihenstephan, Germany</conf-loc>
               
               <conf-date>
                  March 7-10
               </conf-date>
               
               <publisher-name>Verlag Dr. Köster</publisher-name>
               <fpage>342</fpage>
               <lpage>345</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="R08">
            <element-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <article-title>Ökologischer Landbau in Deutschland, Stand: Januar 2018</article-title>
               <publisher-name>Bundesministerium für Ernährung und Landwirtschaft</publisher-name>
               <year>2018</year>
               <publisher-loc>Bonn, Germany</publisher-loc>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="R09">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1079/raf2005110</pub-id>
               <year>2005</year>
               <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press (CUP)</publisher-name>
               <volume>20</volume>
               <issue>04</issue>
               <fpage>243</fpage>
               <lpage>251</lpage>
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>C.S. Wortmann</surname>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>A.P. Christiansen</surname>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>K.L. Glewen</surname>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>T.A. Hejny</surname>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>J. Mulliken</surname>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>J.M. Peterson</surname>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>D.L. Varner</surname>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>S. Wortmann</surname>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>G.L. Zoubek</surname>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <article-title>Farmer research: Conventional experiences and guidelines for alternative agriculture and multi-functional agro-ecosystems</article-title>
               <source>Renewable Agriculture and Food Systems</source>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="R10">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12924/of2015.01010001</pub-id>
               <year>2013</year>
               <publisher-name>Librello</publisher-name>
               <volume>1</volume>
               <issue>1</issue>
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Thomas Felix Döring</surname>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <article-title>A Fresh Start for Organic Farming Research</article-title>
               <source>Organic Farming</source>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
