<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMed 2.0//EN" "http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov:80/entrez/query/static/PubMed.dtd">
<ArticleSet><Article><Journal><PublisherName>Librello</PublisherName><JournalTitle>Challenges in Sustainability</JournalTitle><Issn>2297-6477</Issn><Volume>5</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate PubStatus="epublish"><Year>2017</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>03</Day></PubDate></Journal><ArticleTitle>Sustainability Science in the Light of Urban Planning</ArticleTitle><FirstPage>26</FirstPage><LastPage>34</LastPage><ELocationID EIdType="doi">10.12924/cis2017.05010026</ELocationID><Language>EN</Language><AuthorList><Author><FirstName>François</FirstName><LastName>Mancebo</LastName><Affiliation>International Research Center on Sustainability, Rheims University, Rheims, France. francois.mancebo@univ-reims.fr</Affiliation></Author></AuthorList><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pii">cis-5.1.26</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><History><PubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2016</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>03</Day></PubDate><PubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2016</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>06</Day></PubDate><PubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2016</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>18</Day></PubDate></History><Abstract>The purpose of this article is to demonstrate that, as part of its mission, sustainability science can change the way planners engage with urban problems on three points: First, that effective standard planning is an illusion, and the crucial task for urban planners should be considering—on a place-based rationale—the long-term consequences of decisions, policies and, technology change. Second,how it is necessary to develop collaborative planning and co-production of knowledge. Third, to build effective actions on the basis of collaborative planning, it is crucial to take first into account how the population and the institutions respond to and resist change. Conversely, this paper shows that urban planning is also a breeding ground for consolidating the theoretical framework of sustainability science, considering that cities can be seen as paragons of both socio-ecological systems and complex adaptive systems—a position that is discussed throughout the article. Bringing sustainability science and urban planning in closer dialogue with each other, to exploit their potential synergies, has not been done sufficiently: It is an important gap in the academic literature that this article aims at filling.</Abstract></Article></ArticleSet>
