<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMed 2.0//EN" "http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov:80/entrez/query/static/PubMed.dtd">
<ArticleSet><Article><Journal><PublisherName>Librello</PublisherName><JournalTitle>Challenges in Sustainability</JournalTitle><Issn>2297-6477</Issn><Volume>10</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate PubStatus="epublish"><Year>2022</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>06</Day></PubDate></Journal><ArticleTitle>Systems Dynamics Model of SDGs: A Case Study of Iran</ArticleTitle><FirstPage>3</FirstPage><LastPage>22</LastPage><ELocationID EIdType="doi">10.12924/cis2022.10010003</ELocationID><Language>EN</Language><AuthorList><Author><FirstName>Mojgan</FirstName><LastName>Chapariha</LastName><Affiliation>Lisbon School of Economics and Management (ISEG), University of Lisbon, Lisbon, Portugal. mojgan@phd.iseg.ulisboa.pt</Affiliation></Author></AuthorList><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pii">cis-10.1.3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><History><PubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2021</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>24</Day></PubDate><PubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2021</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>29</Day></PubDate></History><Abstract>This paper investigates on the implementation Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs) in Iran. It generates a systems dynamics model for exploring possibilities for achieving four SDGs: SDG-1 (eradicating poverty), SDG-8 (economic growth and decent work), SDG-12 (sustainable production and consumption), and SDG-13 (climate action) in Iran. The model is used to generate four possible stories about the implementation of measures to achieve these SDGs in the future of the Iranian economy from 2020 to 2050: 1) the Scenario of Business as Usual continues current trends and projects them into the future, 2) the Scenario of Inclusive Growth is designed to simulate more income equality and faster economic growth, 3) the Scenario of a Steady State introduces measures to improve social, and environmental aspects while having zero economic growth, and 4) the Scenario of Well-being for People and Planet is designed to improve socio-economic and environmental aspects of the Iranian economy to achieve the four SDGs in Iran. The performance of the Iranian economy for progressing towards the SDGs is monitored through four SDG indexes which are measured based on the arithmetic mean of selected indicators for each SDG, and a Combined Index of SDGs which is measured based on the arithmetic mean of the four SDGs indexes. The results of the simulations of the SDGs model of Iran shows that the transformational scenarios (Steady State, and Well-being for People and Planet) provide better pathways in comparison to conventional scenarios (Business as Usual and Inclusive Growth) for achieving the SDGs. Moreover, this study find that transformational policy changes and extraordinary efforts are required for progress in achieving SDGs in Iran.</Abstract></Article></ArticleSet>
