<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="research-article"
         dtd-version="3.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">cis</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title xml:lang="en">Challenges in Sustainability</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">2297-6477</issn>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Librello</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12924/cis2016.04010001</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Editorial</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Urban Agriculture: Fostering the Urban-Rural Continuum</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <name>
                  <surname>Mancebo</surname>
                  <given-names>Francois</given-names>
               </name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">*</xref>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">1</xref>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <name>
                  <surname>Salles</surname>
                  <given-names>Sylvie</given-names>
               </name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">2</xref>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <aff id="A1">
            <label>*</label>Corresponding author</aff>
         <aff id="A2">
            <label>1</label>International Research Center on Sustainability, Rheims University, Rheims, France</aff>
         <aff id="A3">
            <label>2</label>Ecole d'Architecture Paris Val de Seine, Paris, France</aff>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <day>20</day>
            <month>04</month>
            <year>2016</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>4</volume>
         <issue>1</issue>
         <fpage>1</fpage>
         <lpage>2</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-year>2005</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec id="s1">
            <title></title>
         <p>
            Urban agricultural projects have been mushrooming since
            the end of the twentieth century, reshaping urban landscapes and even the whole urban fabric, experimenting
            with alternatives to the traditional urban life, sometimes creating new commons, and bringing people together. Within
            a city, farmers, gardeners, and their neighbors share more
            than just fence lines. Cities already have a huge potential for farming. Three examples can be observed in very
            different cities around the World: Singapore, is fully selfreliant in meat, Bamako is self-sufficient in vegetables, and
            in Berlin there are 80,000 community gardens on communal land and 16,000 more people are on a waiting-list [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R01">1</xref>].
            And this is just the beginning; in many cities new unbuilt
            areas emerge in the wake of deindustrialization (derelict
            lands, wastelands, brownfields, etc.), or as a consequence
            of urban shrinking due to aging populations (as in Japan or
            Germany), or of emigration (as in some African mid-sized
            cities). These new areas are a wonderful opportunity for
            urban agriculture. In Detroit, thousands hectares of urban
            land have been given over to unemployed workers for food
            growing. In Britain, urban agriculture has been promoted on
            wastelands of 20 cities by their various councils [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R02">2</xref>]. Urban
            agriculture is gradually becoming a planning policy option.
            In Delft, the planners of the city already combine urban
            agriculture with several other land uses in their planning
            documents; in Paris, an inclusive local land development
            plan protects agricultural landscapes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04">4</xref>]. Urban agriculture is neither—or no more—the short-lived remnant of a
            rural culture nor the hipsters’ latest futile craze.
            
         </p>
         <p>
            et, on the face of it, tying together these two words—
            urban and agriculture—is not self-evident, even if city and
            agriculture have gone hand in hand for a long time: in fact,
            since Neolithic times and the first human settlements, as
            pointed by Paul Bairoch [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. Jane Jacobs even promotes
            the idea that agriculture is of urban origin, and it was only
            later that agriculture migrates to the countryside—this was a
            very slow process [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R06">6</xref>]. It was only in the middle of the 
            Twentieth Century, in the aftermath of the WW2, that cities and
            agriculture—which had always been inseparable—divorced.
            Increased mobility and progressive globalization made apparently pointless proximity between farmers and urban
            consumers. Farming was banned from the city by planning
            regulation. Urban agriculture suffered then from many political restraints: restrictive urban policy, laws giving an illegal
            status to urban agriculture, lack of supportive services, etc.
            Hopefully things are changing, and urban agriculture is being welcomed again in the city after an unfortunate interlude
            of some fifty years. Still in the Ninetieth Century the close
            interaction between city and farming could be read in the
            landscape and in the planning instruments and procedures.
            In 1826, Von Thunen’s theory explained agricultural patterns near urban areas—in the form of concentric circles,
            with crop type being determined by transport cost-distance
            modeling. It was maybe a rough and restrictive draft of
            what we coin today as the importance of addressing the
            rural-urban continuum to deal with urban sustainability. Indeed, talking about urban sustainability is meaningless if we
            stop at the city limits. Everyone agrees today to consider
            that sustainable urban policies should take into account
            an urban-rural continuum that goes far beyond the dense
            mineral town within its administrative limits.
         </p>
         <p>
            Urban agriculture may help designing truly sustainable
            policies for such complex settings. We need to question
            and discuss ways to include, in a perennial manner, agriculture in urban policies. Urban agriculture can be seen
            as a process of hybridization between city and agriculture,
            which offers many advantages over other expressions of
            nature in the city. In addition to allowing the development of
            agricultural production, being consistent with the aspirations
            of urban populations wishing to reconnect with nature, and
            providing many ecosystem services, urban agriculture also
            provides new opportunities for developers to rethink the
            organization of the urban fabric. To facilitate this, there is a
            need for knowledge building (sharing examples, procedures,
            comparing different places), which should take the form of
            a co-production of knowledge by all the actors involved in
            urban agriculture actions through the world. Confronting
            and integrating values and knowledge from different stakeholders is crucial to help decision-making. This task was
            initiated by the international conference <italic>5 emes
            Rencontres
            Internationales de Reims on Sustainability Science</italic> whose
            theme was precisely “Urban Agriculture: Fostering The
            Urban-Rural Continuum”. Most of the articles in this special
            issue of Challenges in Sustainability were presented on the
            occasion of this conference.
         </p>
         <p>
            To capsulize into a few words what was the guiding
            thread throughout the conference, and therefore the unifying idea of this special issue beyond the diversity of the
            papers, the following can be said: When trying to determine
            if urban agriculture may contribute to a sustainable future,
            the primary question to ask is: Will this agriculture be at
            the service of the inhabitants? Its success depends on its
            objectives, its form, and its local ownership by the people
            concerned. It has a lot to do with building resilient communities. By doing so, urban agriculture can be the cornerstone
            that helps reconfigure more sustainable cities.
         </p>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back>
      <ref-list>
         <ref id="R01">
            <element-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <source>Urban Agriculture: Food, Jobs and Sustainable cities</source>
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Smit</surname>
                     <given-names>Jac</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Nasr</surname>
                     <given-names>Joe</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Ratta</surname>
                     <given-names>Annu</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <publisher-loc>New York, NY, USA</publisher-loc>
               <publisher-name>United Nations Development Programme</publisher-name>
               <year>1996</year>
               <comment>Series for Habitat II</comment>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="R02">
            <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <article-title>Urban agriculture and sustainable cities</article-title>
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Deelstra</surname>
                     <given-names>Tjeerd</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Girardet</surname>
                     <given-names>Herbert</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>others</surname>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <source>Bakker N., Dubbeling M., Gündel S., Sabel-Koshella U., de Zeeuw H. Growing cities, growing food. Urban agriculture on the policy agenda. Feldafing, Germany: Zentralstelle für Ernährung und Landwirtschaft (ZEL)</source>
               <fpage>43</fpage>
               <lpage>66</lpage>
               <year>2000</year>
               <publisher-name>Citeseer</publisher-name>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="R03">
            <element-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <source>Growing better cities: Urban agriculture for sustainable development</source>
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Mougeot</surname>
                     <given-names>Luc J. A.</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>2006</year>
               <publisher-name>International Development Research Centre</publisher-name>
               <publisher-loc>Ottawa, Canada</publisher-loc>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="R04">
            <element-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Mancebo</surname>
                     <given-names>F.</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Isenhour</surname>
                     <given-names>C and McDonough, G and Checker, M</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <source>Sustainability in the Global City: Myth and Practice</source>
               <chapter-title>Combining Sustainability and Social Justice in the Paris Metropolitan Region</chapter-title>
               <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
               <year>2015</year>
               <source>Series New Directions in Sustainability</source>
               <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>
               <fpage>263</fpage>
               <lpage>283</lpage>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="R05">
            <element-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <source>De Jericho \`a Mexico, villes et \'economie dans l’histoire</source>
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Paul</surname>
                     <given-names>Bairoch</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <year>1985</year>
               <publisher-name>Gallimard</publisher-name>
               <publisher-loc>Paris, France</publisher-loc>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="R06">
            <element-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <name name-style="western">
                     <surname>Jacobs</surname>
                     <given-names>J.</given-names>
                  </name>
               </person-group>
               <source>The Economy of the City</source>
               <publisher-name>Random House</publisher-name>
               <year>1969</year>
               <publisher-loc>New York, NY, USA</publisher-loc>
            </element-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
