<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMed 2.0//EN" "http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov:80/entrez/query/static/PubMed.dtd">
<ArticleSet><Article><Journal><PublisherName>Librello</PublisherName><JournalTitle>Challenges in Sustainability</JournalTitle><Issn>2297-6477</Issn><Volume>8</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate PubStatus="epublish"><Year>2020</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>08</Day></PubDate></Journal><ArticleTitle>Residential Photovoltaic Systems in Norway: Household Knowledge, Preferences and Willingness to Pay</ArticleTitle><FirstPage>1</FirstPage><LastPage>16</LastPage><ELocationID EIdType="doi">10.12924/cis2020.08010001</ELocationID><Language>EN</Language><AuthorList><Author><FirstName>Todd</FirstName><MiddleName>L.</MiddleName><LastName>Cherry</LastName><Affiliation>CICERO Center for International Climate Research, Oslo, Norway\\&#13;
Appalachian State University, North Carolina, USA. cherrytl@appstate.edu</Affiliation></Author><Author><FirstName>Hanne</FirstName><LastName>Sæle</LastName><Affiliation>Department of Energy Systems, SINTEF Energy Research, Trondheim, Norway. Hanne.Saele@sintef.no</Affiliation></Author></AuthorList><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pii">cis-8.1.1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><History><PubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2019</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>05</Day></PubDate><PubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2019</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>31</Day></PubDate><PubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2019</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>29</Day></PubDate></History><Abstract>Solar power or photovoltaic (PV) systems have emerged as a leading low-carbon energy technology worldwide, but the deployment of residential PV systems in Norway has lagged behind other Scandinavian countries. Therefore, the Norwegian market provides an opportunity to gain insights on the demand factors that determine residential PV adoption. This paper presents results from a stated-preference survey designed to elicit household knowledge, preferences and willingness to pay for residential PV systems. Results suggest that meaningful growth in residential PV capacity depends greater knowledge among households, continued advances in technology, clarity with the grid tariff and stronger support systems. A review of recent experiences in the field corroborates the important role of effective regulatory structures and support programs.</Abstract></Article></ArticleSet>
